Never forget why you are the church.
I want you to go ahead this morning.
We'll go right into scripture.
I've got a lot to teach today, so go ahead and go to Romans chapter 9.
Romans chapter 9.
I got some sound in the background of my preaching.
I like it, man.
That's cool.
It'll build as we go.
know what I'm saying?
Romans chapter 9.
This morning, we're gonna continue right along.
We were looking at the biblical doctrine of mercy.
What does God, or who does God show mercy to?
Why does he show mercy to them?
We have to understand this chapter all the way through chapter
11 is being primarily written to
the Jewish community in Rome.
To them, because they were Israelites, there was no doubt
that they would be saved, no matter what, yet most of them completely
rejected Jesus as the Messiah.
I want you to know something.
These 2 statements are not compatible.
You cannot be saved and reject Jesus Christ.
Peter, fill with the Holy Ghost at the day of Pentecost, declare
there is only one way to salvation.
That's in Acts chapter 4, verse 12.
Neither is there salvation in any other.
For there is none other name under heaven given among
men whereby we must be saved.
If you wonder why we sing about the name of Jesus so much.
If you wonder why we pray in the name of Jesus so much, if
you wonder why I teach and preach the name of Jesus so
much, is because it's the only name that can save you and I.
The most important thing you can hear today is this,
to reject Jesus, is to reject God.
This new age garbage, which really is not new age, but it's
coming to be even more and more that claims that a person can
have their own thing and their own agreement and their
own little deal with God is a lie straight
from the devil.
God has one plan from the beginning.
To send his only begotten son, Jesus, to
this earth, to take on the form of man.
Fully God, fully man, tempted and tried,
as we are, yet without sin, falsely accuse
and crucified as a criminal between 2 real criminals.
His blood sheds so that we can be forgiven, the crown
of thorns, the nails in his perfect hands, and feet,
the public humiliation, and flogging, and
beating all for us.
He cried out, it is finished, the precious
lamb of God died on the rugged cross.
They put them in a tomb and put a heavy stone to seal it.
First they went by.
Second day it went by.
Could you imagine the hopelessness?
that was going on with his followers.
But then the 3rd day came.
Y'all need to get a little more excited about some resurrection here this morning.
The 3rd day he came.
And guess what happened?
Well, we know what happened.
Three days later, everything changed.
He was raised from the dead, defeating death, hell in the grave,
and in doing so, we can as well.
What is the point of me saying all this?
Exactly what Peter said.
Neither is there salvation in any other.
For there is none other name under heaven given among men
whereby we must be saved.
So today I'm asking you, would you put your faith in Jesus today?
This is Paul's whole point of writing this letter.
to bring people to Jesus.
He was heartbroken about those that was his brethren
rejecting Christ.
So so far, we've looking at the unexplainable mercy of
God, and we've seen, number one, the people of mercy.
Romans 9, verse 6 says, not as though the word of
God had taken none effect, for they are not all Israel,
which are of Israel.
Again, a title is unexplainable, mercy.
Let's pray.
Father, I thank you for your word.
God I thank you, Lord, just for the spirit of just attention.
God today, God, I pray, Lord, with the holy hush, God,
that those that have ears to hear, may they hear.
And God, I pray that we trust your plan no matter what.
And God, we thank you that you are merciful, God.
We thank you that you are faithful and good.
We thank you for your plan, God, that included us.
God, we thank you, we love you, since Jesus ain't praying.
And everybody said, amen.
I don't know if you notice not, but I just share the gospel there, buddy, here.
There's many ways to share the gospel.
This is just one gospel, though.
Amen?
So there's certain details that you have to hit regardless of how you do it.
But I was reading a Facebook post and this is why I'm trying to tell you that this new age stuff.
You gotta be careful with it.
And this scholar, this pastor of a
church, said, hey, listen, to new pastors.
This is some fine things that you need to need to listen to, right?
Well, I'm not a new pastor, but I'm always good to learn.
So let's see what this guy has to say.
Well, I didn't get past number three.
You know what number 3 was?
You don't have to share the gospel every time you preach.
Kids cover your ears.
That's stupid.
I mean, that's dumb.
I mean, We are here because of the gospel.
You take the gospel away, you might as well go home.
You take the gospel away.
listen, all of this is for naught.
I'm just going to let you know right now, listen, Paul knew how important the gospel.
He even said, listen, hey, the gospel is even more important than anything else.
I want to share the gospel.
So the reader of this letter would have some troubling thoughts
about the fact that most of their fellow Israelites were not born again.
again, they had rejected Christ.
Does this mean that God's word had failed, right?
This is the question that no doubt came to their mind.
See, God promised Abraham that he would become a mighty
nation, and through that nation, the whole world would be blessed.
This is speaking of the nation of Israel.
So how can some Israelites be saved and others not?
Well, that brings up number two.
We've seen the people of mercy, right?
We're going to see the plan of mercy.
Paul begins to narrow down who is truly the promised people.
Just being a descendant of Abraham was not enough.
If so, this everlasting covenant would apply
to Ishmael as well.
But then he narrows it down even more.
In Romans 9, verse 9 through 13, he says this.
For this is the word of promise, at this time will I come, and
Sarah shall have a son.
And not only this, but when Rebecca also had conceived
by one, even by our father Isaac, for the children being
not yet born, neither having done any good or evil,
that the purpose of God, according to election, might stand,
not of works, but of him that calleth.
Romans, if you look at verse 12,
it says it was said unto her, the elder shall serve the younger,
as it is written, Jacob, have I loved, but Esau, have I hated.
So we're narrowing down who are the covenant people.
This text has nothing to do necessarily with the
salvation of Jacob and Esau.
It has everything to do with God's higher choice.
He chose to continue the Abrahamic covenant through
Jacob rather than Esau.
Now, Paul then answers the question and undoubtedly entered the
minds of his readers, then and today.
Verse 14 says this, what shall we say then?
Is there unrighteousness with God?
Now I'm going to warn you today.
Because this text was really written for a Jewish
audience originally.
It is going to be very heavy with Old Testament.
Okay?
So just like 2 weeks ago, when we were in the Old Testament
a whole lot, we're going to be in the Old Testament a whole lot today as well.
All right?
And so if you if you are trying to keep up, because
I got a lot of things to say, jot it down, and guess what?
We want to learn about God increasingly, go home and study it for yourself.
Amen?
I mean, I mean, I just the only challenge I can give you.
I'm going to do my best to hit as much as possible.
But I'm going to tell you right now.
I may not be able to answer every question.
Right?
Let me remind you what Peter said about Paul's writings.
Sometimes it's hard to understand, okay?
So don't expect every answer for everything.
Listen, there's faith that has to be involved in this.
Amen.
So again, let's get into it.
What shall we say then?
Is there unrighteousness with God?
By choosing Isaac over Ishmael.
Jacob over Esau.
Does this make God unjust?
Now, listen, we understand that, but you do realize that the
biggest argument against believing in God is
because those who don't believe in him, who don't know him, who
have not studied the word of God with the unction, the Holy Spirit, they
think, well, if God is real, how can evil happen?
If God is real, why does death happen?
If God is real, why do people get sick, good people get sick.
Why do evil people live to be a hundred, but good people have
to don't.
If God is real, how can he be so, quote unquote unrighteous?
So this is a very serious thing that we have to understand here.
Because people were excused putting their faith in
him by saying, I can't believe an unjust God.
And let's just be honest here, it's not a question that Bible studiers have not asked themselves.
When we look at this from the perspective of our human facilities, it is easy
to think God unjust, how could he choose one and not
the other, just a cold read?
Man, that's kind of not fair for Esau?
If you read the story of in Genesis about Ishmael,
I mean, man, your heart has to break for Ishmael.
But again, Paul, in his normal emphatic way, answers this question.
What shall we then say?
Is there unrighteous with God?
What does he say?
God forbid.
He then gives the explanation.
Romans 9.15
For he say it to Moses, I will have mercy on whom I will have mercy.
And I will have compassion on whom I will have compassion.
Paul is quoting Exodus 3319 and he said, I will
make all my goodness pass before thee, and I will proclaim
the name of the Lord before thee, and will be gracious to whom I will be gracious and
will show mercy on whom I will show mercy.
Now, listen, again, let's not sit here in our self
righteousness in our buckle, the Bible belt mentality,
and think that when we read that, we don't go, hmm.
See, that hits our finite minds kind of hard.
In our society, what we do is we try to equate
God's mercy with God being fair.
It's not fair that some get mercy and others do not.
It's not fair for God to have compassion on some and not on others.
As a matter of fact, I guarantee you that you have used
the phrase, it's just not fair.
Adults use it all the time, right?
Listen, hey, some of y'all are going to get to sit on the pew on the float.
Some of you gonna get there too late and get kicked off.
It's not fair, preacher.
My kids, listen, my kids all the time, and Ridley's
the worst of them, man.
I don't know what it is, but River would do something and Ridley wants to
do something, and River just got in trouble for doing it.
So obviously we can't let Ridley do it, and really go, well, she did,
and she doesn't know the phrase, it's not fair, but what she's
saying is that's not fair.
And then, you know, some of your better parents might say something better.
I say, well, tough.
Sometimes you don't have anything to say.
You know what I'm saying?
It's just like, I'm sorry, you know?
But here's the thing.
It's funny how we want
fairness, but we don't understand what that truly means
inside of God.
What I'm trying to say is this.
If God was fair, no one would get mercy.
Y'all with me this morning?
Don't don't leave me here.
If God was fair, No one would get mercy.
Mercy, and of itself is contradictory to the concept of fairness.
Webster defines the concept of fair like this,
marked by impartiality and honesty, free from self-interest,
prejudice, or favoritism, conforming to what is good, just, and proper.
Now, I know what you're thinking.
Man, that definition of fair sounds good to me.
The issue is for God to be fair.
He must give everyone what they deserve.
And because God is holy, righteous,
just, and completely good, he cannot look
upon sin without judging it.
Therefore, if God was fair, we
would all be condemned.
With no hope.
Romans 3, 10, and 11, as it is written, there is none righteous, no, not one.
Not you, not the person beside you, not your precious granny.
Not one.
There's none that understand that there's none that seeketh after God.
So throw the concept of fair out.
We don't want a fair God.
We want a merciful God.
The plan of mercy sent Jesus to Calvary to die for our sins,
the plan of mercy provided the power to resurrect Christ from the
dead, the plan of mercy offers salvation to all who placed
their faith in Jesus Christ.
There's a song that Gordon Moat wrote.
Gordon Moat wrote, and he put this in the lyrics, and it's
called when Mercy walked in and says this.
I stood in the courtroom.
The judge turned my way.
It looks like you're guilty.
Now what do you say?
I spoke up, your honor, I have no defense.
But that's when mercy walked in.
Mercy walked in and pleaded my case, called to the stand.
God saving grace.
The blood was presented that covered my sin forgiven
when mercy walked in.
I stood there and wondered, how could this be?
Someone so guilty had just been set free.
My chains were broken.
I felt born again the moment that mercy walked in.
Called to the stand, God saving grace.
The blood was presented that covered my sin forgiven when
mercy walked in.
Aren't you glad we serve a merciful God?
Romans 9.16, we're going to continue because Paul explains,
so then it is not of him that willeth, nor of him that runneth,
but of God that showeth mercy.
Mercy has nothing to do with what we do.
It's not based on our actions or merit.
It's based on God's choice.
No one deserves or can earn mercy.
Now we get to another controversial portion of the text and
we get to the example of pharaoh.
What do we do with Pharaoh?
Let's look at it right here.
Romans 9, 17, and 18?
For the scripture saith unto Pharaoh, even for the
same purpose have I raised thee up, that I might show
my power in thee.
And that my name might be declared throughout all the earth.
Therefore hath he mercy on whom he will have mercy, and
whom he will, he hardeneth.
Now.
Let's not forget the context of Paul's exposition.
He is informing the Jews in Rome of why most of
Israel has rejected Christ.
He is clarifying who is God's people and who is not God's people.
He is explaining the God's plan of salvation,
not necessarily salvation itself.
Verses 6 through 9.
He declares that we do not get this status of God's people
by blood, that is simply being of the seed of Abraham.
Verses 10 through 13.
He declares it's not by works.
Here he declares it is only by mercy,
and he brings up Pharaoh's role in the Great Exodus.
If God hardened his heart.
Now, hear me.
I going to ask the question that was asked.
If God did solely bring him into existence,
in order to make it impossible for him to trust God,
If Pharaoh was simply a pawn in a way to show off God's power,
Where does that leave us?
If God hardened Pharaoh's heart,
Does that mean that he can harden mine?
It's a pretty serious question, is it not?
Do you understand what it means to have your heart, heart and my God,
you would probably be more urgent and, hey, I need to know this answer.
So that's what we're going to look at.
Two women say amen.
Okay.
To answer that, though, we must understand why God hardens hearts in the 1st place.
Pharaoh might be the greatest example of this, but Paul mentions a
form of hardening right here in Romans itself.
All the way back in chapter one, verses 18 and 19, for the wrath of
God is revealed from heaven against all ungodliness and unrighteousness
of men who hold the truth in unrighteousness.
Because that which may be known of God has manifested them, for God
has showed it unto them.
In other words, we see here, just like Israel, right, was rejecting
Christ, just like Pharaoh rejected, rejected God, right?
We see that Paul is talking about those who are
withholding the truth, who are living and unrighteous, those who are lost.
Rejecting God, rejecting the truth.
So the result in Romans 124, wherefore God
also gave them up to uncleanness,
to the lust of their own hearts, to dishonor their own bodies between themselves.
Now, he uses this phrase, gave them up,
again, in Romans one, verse 26, 2 verses down.
For this cause, God gave them up unto vile affections.
What does it mean God gave them up or gave them over?
Well, the Greek term for that means to hand over
to entrust to commit.
We see this in other parts of scripture as well.
Jesus used it in speaking of his crucifixion in
Matthew 20, verse 17 through 19.
It says this, and Jesus, going up to Jerusalem,
took the 12 disciples apart in the way and said unto them,
behold, we go up to Jerusalem, and the Son
of Man shall be betrayed unto the chief priests and unto
the scribes, and they shall condemn him to death and shall deliver.
That word deliver is the same term here
used, gave them up to entrust,
to hand over, to commit, and shall deliver him.
That's Jesus to the Gentiles, to mock and discourge
and the crucify him.
And the 3rd day, he shall rise again.
Again, that word delivers the same term for Gabe in Romans
chapter one, once Jesus was delivered or rather committed
to the Gentiles for his death.
listen, it was a done deal.
In other words, there was no getting out of it.
Now, don't hear what I'm not saying.
God is all powerful.
If he wanted to call allegiance angels up to destroy those who
are hurting him, he could have.
But the work of Calvary had to be done for the saving of our souls.
So the plan of mercy involved God handing
over his son.
We see this finale of the term used in a positive context in Jude 3.
I told you, we were going, we were doing a lot of stuff here this morning.
Jude three, beloved, when I gave all diligence
to write unto you, the common salvation.
It was needful for me to write unto you and exhort you
that you should earnestly contend for the faith which was once
delivered unto the saints.
Again, that word delivered, to entrust, to commit, to hand over.
You say, well, you said something about finality.
Well, if you look at the rendering of the NASB 95.
Look what it says.
He says, I'm writing to you appealing that you contend
earnestly for the faith, which was once for
all handed down to the saints.
What does that mean?
That same faith that Jude challenged the saints to contend for?
It's the same faith that we're contending for today.
Amen?
And because it was delivered once and for all, it'll be the same faith
to contend for as long as God tarries.
We could be here for another 1000 years.
Guess what?
There's going to be churches doing exactly what we're doing.
contending for the faith in Jesus Christ.
Why?
Because it was committed.
Delivered unto the saints.
Y'all still with me, say amen.
So what does this have to do with the question of God hardening my heart?
Well, it is obvious that the people God gave up in Romans one were not his children.
In other words, they were lost.
Paul says they were given to a reprobate mind.
That word reprobate means bad and depraved.
Many translators use the term unacceptable and even worthless.
Now, how could this be?
Because they rejected God because God gave them up, what were they filled with then?
Well, they were filled with exactly what they were filled with when they rejected.
God.
you're not there.
on the screen, but Romans one, verse 29 and 32 being filled
with awe unrighteousness, fornication, wickedness, covishness, maliciousness,
full of envy, murder, debate, deceit, malignity, whisperers,
backbiters, haters of God, despiteful, proud, boasters,
inventors of evil things, disobedient to parents, without
understanding, covenant breakers, without natural affection,
implacable, unmerciful, who knowing the judgment
of God, that they which commit such things are worthy of death, not only
do the same, but have pleasure in them that do them.
Paul tells in 1st Corinthians chapter 6 that those who practice live
in such things will not inherit the kingdom of God.
But we just saw that
God giving them up means to entrust,
commit, and hand over.
Some people may say, well, I don't believe that's a permanent thing.
Well, if they die walking.
Rejecting Christ and living according
to all these things we just said.
The Bible says, They're not going to heaven.
So God gave them up.
Now.
I say all that to say this before we go on to Pharaoh.
I don't see scripture ever indicating.
that God can give up.
Who's his?
In other words, if you are a child of God.
You won't be giving up.
By the way, if you're worried about being given up, you're probably not giving up.
If you're worried about your sin, if you're, if you have conviction in
your life, That's not God in
trusting you over to a reverent mind.
No, no, no, that's you being led by the Holy Spirit of living
God, convicting you and guiding you and leading you.
So again, we're going to shift our attention to the example of Pharaoh, because it's
going to all kind of make sense here in just a second.
People love to shout from the rooftop.
Well, God hardened his heart and he had no choice in the matter.
Well, that does not necessarily align with what we can read all throughout Exodus.
Now, I can find you a verse, and I'll read it to you, and you'll be like, yep, told you.
But see, as biblical mature
studiers, you want to study all
of it, not just one of it.
Amen?
Whenever someone tries to build a theology or doctrinal
statement on one verse, run.
They're trying to get something they want in that verse
and it's not what God planned for it.
So anyway, Well, looking at here, if
you go back to Exodus chapter 3, when God instructed Moses to
go to Pharaoh, what did he tell him?
Exodus chapter 3, verse 19.
And I am sure that the king of Egypt will not let you go.
No, not by a mighty hand.
God already knew Pharaoh's heart.
By the way, I want you to know something.
God knows you as well.
He knows your heart, but later in the next chapter,
God doubles down on this.
And the Lord said unto Moses, when thou goest to return into
Egypt, see that thou do all those wonders before Pharaoh,
which I have put in thy hand, but I will harden his heart so that
he shall not let the people go.
Now, I want to take a few steps back because I want to make sure
everyone's understanding where we're at in the grand scheme of things here.
Right?
Moses, okay, grew up in Egypt, right?
saw his fellow Hebrews getting abused,
ended up being exiled because he killed an
Egyptian for hurting a Hebrew.
So we go into exile and in exile, God calls him to go and
deliver his people out of bondage of Egypt.
So you got 10 plagues, things happening.
So that's kind of the timeline that we're in right now.
Okay?
everyone there with me?
Okay, if you got question about that,
You can ask me after, we can have a little Bible study.
But either way,
So then there we have it.
God unjustly hardened Pharaoh's heart.
How unjust can God be with that?
What does the word harden mean?
This is what we don't understand so often.
Look at what this word harder means real quick.
To grow firm, strong, and strengthened.
So the Hebrew term for harden that God is using here means
to grow firm, Strong and strengthened.
Well, how does that work with the context of what's going on here?
We have to remember, the original language of the Bible were
much deeper than our English language today.
So when God hardened Pharaoh's heart, hear me.
He was strengthening or firming up
an already present rebellious heart posture.
You hear me?
Do we see this kind of fruition?
Exodus five, verse one and two.
And afterward, Moses and Aaron went in and told Pharaoh, thus said the
Lord God of Israel, let my people go.
that they may hold a feast unto me in the wilderness.
And Pharaoh said this, who is the Lord?
That I should obey his voice and let Israel go.
I know not the Lord, neither do I let Israel go.
In other words, Pharaoh saying, I don't know your God, and I'm not going to listen to your God.
He rebelled, rejected.
His heart posture was against God.
There's no mention of God hardening his heart, but here, rather
an exposing of a rebellious heart.
He immediately and emphatically rejected God.
Could it be that God raised that pharaoh knowing that he would be strong against his people?
Let's not forget how we were introduced to this new pharaoh in Exodus
chapter one, verse 7 and 8, and the children of Israel
were fruitful and increased abundantly and multiplied
and waxed exceeding mighty, and the land was filled with them.
Man, it was a good time to be an Israelite.
Now.
There arose up a king, a new king over Egypt, which
knew not Joseph.
Let me explain just briefly what's going on here.
Joseph, his brothers.
I'm trying to give you a synopsis of a very long situation, okay?
Joseph and his brothers, right?
Joseph had some dreams.
How you going to bow down to me, right?
His older brothers didn't like that, sold them to slavery?
He ended up going to Egypt.
Long story short, he ends up being 2nd in command in Egypt.
Okay?
So then his family comes back because there's a
famine in the land and it's like, we're hungry, we need food.
Long story short, they're reconciled.
God works everything out, right?
And they stay in Egypt because he has a blessing
and a favor from the king of Egypt at the time.
Well, now, that king's gone.
Joseph's gone.
And the new king doesn't remember any of that.
All I see is a potential enemy of people
coming into our country, our nation, being able to
be bigger than we are, and if they ever wanted to join with our enemies, we'd be defeated.
So, He didn't like them.
So we put them under hard labor.
He put them under bondage.
He put them under basically slavery, Hebrew slaves.
But again, We see here, um,
We fast forward, but we don't we don't serve a passive God.
We serve a very active.
He's a part of everything.
So we're going to fast forward to Exodus chapter 7, and God
says this in our heart and pharaoh's heart, and multiply my
signs and my wonders in the land of Egypt.
But Pharaoh shall not hearken unto you, that I may lay my hand upon Egypt
and bring forth mine armies, and my people, the children of Israel, out
of the land of Egypt by great judgments.
Both these instances, God tells Moses
that he will harden Pharaoh's heart.
But so far has not done so.
Again, I will harden Pharaoh's heart.
In other words, I'm going to do it, but he has not done it yet.
So Moses and Aaron speak to Pharaoh again, and what is his response?
Exodus 713.
And he hardened Pharaoh's heart, and then he hearkened not unto them as the Lord had said.
Now, if you look at another rendering of the NSB 95, right?
The Hebrew actually is worded like this.
Yet Pharaoh's heart was hardened, and he did
not listen to them as the Lord had said.
In other words, no one is necessarily given credit to
hardening his heart.
We do, however, see pharaoh hardening his own heart,
the next chapter in verse 15.
But when Pharaoh saw that there was a spot, he hardened his heart and
hearkened not unto them as the Lord had said.
Now remember, Moses and Aaron are going back and forth to Pharaoh
saying, hey, let my people go.
The Lord God says, let my people go, and every time, right?
His heart is hardened pharaoh's is, he harness
his heart, says, no, I'm not letting your people go.
In the midst of the plagues, instead of turning to God, he continues to rebel,
the word hardened here actually means to
be heavy and burdensome.
In heaviness of heart, he stuck to his stubbornness
and did not let the people go.
He does this again in Exodus 832.
And Pharaoh hardened his heart at this time also.
Neither would he let the people go.
Y'all seeing a trend here?
Some of y'all see in the backyard, Liz.
Wake up.
Amen.
And then we finally get to Exodus chapter 9.
As God sent the boils and pharaoh's magicians could not even
stand before Moses, they were so sick from the boils.
Exodus 912.
And the Lord, harden the heart of Pharaoh.
And he hearkened not unto them.
as the Lord has spoken unto Moses.
There you have it.
Say preacher?
God hardened his heart.
Had no option, couldn't do nothing, couldn't do nothing about it.
That is unjust.
Hear me today.
Pharaoh deserved it.
We want to label this an arbitrary an arbitrary judgment
from God against Pharaoh.
That is, that Pharaoh did not do anything and deserve this.
The judgment was without rational basis or established rule.
Like, God just decided, oh, I'm going to harden Pharaoh's heart.
But that's not, that's not what it was.
This was judicial.
Pharaoh oppressed God's people.
He rejected the command and will of God.
He hardened his own heart numerous times.
So God strengthened that heart posture for his purpose and for his glory.
So if we go back to Romans 9, 18, therefore hath he mercy on whom
he will have mercy and whom he will, he hardeneth.
Well, preacher, I just don't like that.
Well, I'm not going to sit here and lie to you and say that it's, you know, warm and fuzzy for me either.
I mean, I don't like I don't like the concept of God hardening our hearts.
Good thing is I'm already a possession of God.
I can't, you know, The Holy Spirit softens my heart, amen?
But scripture has something to say for those who reject the truth here.
We see Romans 9 versus 19 through 24.
We're going to read it a little bit here.
It says this.
That will say then unto me, why does he yet find fault?
For who has resisted his will?
Nay, but 0 man, who art thou that repliest against God?
Shall the thing formed say to him that formed it?
Why hast thou made me thus?
Have not the pot or power over the clay?
Of the same lump to make one vessel, one to honor, and another unto dishonor?
What if God willing to show his wrath and to make his power known,
endured with much long suffering, the vessels of wrath fitted to destruction?
They might make known the riches of his glory on the best of mercy,
which he had afore prepared on the glory, even us whom he hath called,
not the Jews only, but also the Gentiles.
What he's trying to tell them, is
that because you're rejected, God.
Because you have rejected Jesus.
God is heart in the hearts of Israel.
But how can the clay question the potter?
Now, I don't want to leave this too open-ended.
Again, this is serious.
Understand it.
I can't get all this out in one message.
So I want you to understand that we're going to continue down this road
of under trying to understand God's unexplainable mercy.
But if you are worried, about God giving
you up, That means that he hasn't.
So what do you do, then?
Well, you follow and you respond to that conviction.
You say, well, preacher, you don't know how I've lived.
You don't know what I've done.
You don't know.
listen.
If the Holy Spirit is drawing you unto Christ.
Maybe you're here today and you're lost.
And you're thinking, well, preacher, the sin that I've committed, it
just, there's no way that I could be redeemed.
There's no way that I could be saved.
There's no way.
that I could give my life to Christ.
I've just done too much.
I understand preacher.
You say that you've been saved, but there's no way God could save me.
I want you to know God is never changing.
His will never changes.
His plan never changes and I believe, according to scripture,
when it comes to, hey, his he desires all men to come to the salvation.
I believe that if Pharaoh would have said, you know what?
You're right.
You're God is the only God, and I'm going to serve him.
You know what I believe?
I believe Pharaoh could have been saved.
But that wasn't his heart posture.
His heart posture was rebellious towards God.
So again, what do you do?
If you're worried about God giving you up, that means that he has it.
How to keep your heart from being hard him.
You keep it soft through surrendering to the Lord's will and call.
You keep your heart posture humble before him.
So this morning before we go, I just want to ask you, where is your heart posture right now?
Is your heart posture bent towards rejecting
Christ and rejecting the things of God, rejecting his will for your life?
Maybe God has called you to something and listen,
I don't believe that we can be hardened to the point of being given up,
but I do believe that our sin can cause calluses in our
spirit can cause calluses on our heart to the point to where we don't
sense the things that we once did.
We're not sensitive to the Holy Spirit like we once was.
And so we have a church today that because we're just
going to church, going home, wiping the dust off our Bibles,
we're not having that close relation with God, we're built
to be relational, so therefore we're close to somebody or something,
and usually if it's not God, it means sin.
And so we sin, even as a believer, we sin, and when
walking in rebellion, and we were walking in sin, and
before we know it, we are we are hardened.
The divorce of the Holy Spirit, but you know what's so great about that?
He can overcome it.
That's still small voice, just a little bit can start
cracking that hardening.
You know what I'm saying?
And before you know it, listen, because you're his, and because
he'll never give you up as a believer.
And he'll restore you.
to how you need to be.
But if you're here today, listen to me, and you don't know Jesus.
I'm going to let you know right now.
I'm not I'm not trying to scare you.
I guarantee you.
I have been under preaching.
I've sat under evangelists.
I know how to scare you.
You know what I'm saying?
Like, I could say what I need to say to get a decision today.
That's not my job, though.
My job is to say what he said.
You understand what I'm saying?
Like I'm going according to the word.
I'm not trying to scare you into a decision.
But I can tell you this.
The Bible makes it very clear.
He has mercy on who he has mercy and hardeneth who he hardeneth.
In other words, hey, you're not promised another opportunity of grace tomorrow.
Why walk in sin as a lost person?
First off, you're a believer?
You better repent of your sin, confess it, and get away from it.
But as a lost person.
Yeah, it's your nature.
But right now, you've heard the gospel 3 or 4 times already.
The Holy Spirit right now, as we are sitting here,
think about the miracle of this, the Holy Spirit of the
living God could be drawing you unto his son Jesus.
Pointing it out that you're lost, you need to be saved.
Put your faith in Christ.
Why would you continue experience that, but say, no,
God, not today, and then you just continue to walk.
Let the world, let all the distractions, take
that seed out of your spirit.
Take that seed out of your heart, stomp on it, get rid of
it to where it won't grow.
Before you know it, you've forgotten what you've just experienced here with God.
So you keep on walking.
Next Sunday comes, same thing.
You know why?
Because we're going to preach the gospel every time y'all gather here.
Amen.
So you hear the gospel.
The Holy Spirit is drawing.
Or how about this?
You're studying on a Tuesday.
You're reading the scripture.
The Holy Spirit through his word is drawing you unto Christ.
We say, not today.
And you continue. and continue.
and continue to walk before you know it.
That knocking on that door, that drawing gets weaker.
And weaker and weaker.
before you know it.
God gives you up.
All that means is, okay?
You live how you want to live.
Church, let's not do that.
There's two kinds of people here today.
What Hezban eyes close all over this place, there's two kinds of people.